Guide to the Dorothy Whitcomb Klimper Papers 1904-1975
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Dorothy Whitcomb Klimper Papers
1904-1975
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 395
Klimper, Dorothy Whitcomb, d. 1978
0.3 linear feet
Dorothy Whitcomb Klimper was a resident of Zortman, Montana. This collection includes correspondence, the manuscript, and photographs from the book Top o' the Mountain: Charley Whitcomb, Mining Man, which she co-authored with Gladys Costello.
Biographical Note
Gladys Costello was born in Malta, Montana, the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. H. G. Robinson, who were among the first settlers in the area. She graduated from the University of Montana School of Journalism and maintained a long time interest in writing with a special focus on regional history. In addition to co-authoring Top o' the Mountain: Charley Whitcomb, Mining Man, some of her stories were published in The Golden Era of the Little Rockies. Gladys Costello lived in Zortman, Montana, which is in Phillips County, for most of her adult life until her death on July 16, 1978.
Dorothy Whitcomb Klimper, born in Zortman, was one of two surviving children of Charley and Katie B. Whitcomb. She married Max E. Klimper, mining engineer, educator and sportsman. By 1976 she lived in Stanford, Montana. Costello's writing skills and Klimper's memorabilia and reminiscences were combined for the book Top o' the Mountain: Charley Whitcomb, Mining Man.
This collection includes correspondence, the manuscript, and photos from the book Top o' the Mountain: Charley Whitcomb, Mining Man.
The collection is divided into two series:
Series I: Correspondence and manuscript, 1975
Series II: Photographs, 1904-1971
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Mussoula.
Materials in this collection remained with the creator until donation to the K. Ross Toole Archives.
Gift of Dorothy Klimper, 1976.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Photographs--Montana--Phillips County
Miners--Montana--Zortman--Biography; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Phillips County
Ruby Mine (Phillips County, Mont.); Zortman (Mont.)--Photographs
Whitcomb, Charley, 1866-1936; Costello, Gladys, d. 1978
Klimper family
University of Montana--Missoula--Alumni and alumnae
Montana; Photographs; Mines and Mineral Resources
- Correspondence and manuscript, 1975; Series I
  This series includes four items of correspondence, a miscellaneous note, a poem, a copy of the book manuscript, and photograph captions. Only one piece of correspondence is dated.
  - Costello correspondence and editorial note in regard to manuscript to be self-published, 1975 and undated (Folder 1)
  - Typed draft of manuscript, undated (Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1904-1971; Series II
  This series includes photographs of the Klimper family, friends, business associates, Klimper residences, the Zortman area, and the Ruby mine. Most of the photos were included in the book and their descriptions in this finding aid were taken from captions in the book.
  - Fire above Ruby Gulch, 1936; 395(II)1 (Folder 1)
  - Forest fire that started at Rag Town, undated; 395(II)2 (Folder 2)
  - Whitcomb home in Zortman, Montana, 1905; 395(II)3 (Folder 3)
  - Run-down cabin, undated; 395(II)4; (damaged photo) (Folder 4)
  - Jerry Worthington, George Whitcomb, and Bill Francke (l to r) at goldmelting from first clean-up at Little Ben Mine, 1933; 395(II)5 (Folder 5)
  - Two photos, George Whitcomb in Germany and in Germany with friends, 1919; 395(II)6 (Folder 6)
  - Charles Whitcomb at age 38, 1907; 395(II)7 (Folder 7)
  - Charley Whitcomb and engineer Price discussing the Beaver Creek properties, 1934; 395(II)8 (Folder 8)
  - Unknown man in uniform, undated; 395(II)9 (Folder 9)
  - Unknown man weighing gold samples, undated; 395(II)10 (Folder 10)
  - Third Ruby Gulch Mill, 1936; 395(II)11 (Folder 11)
  - Charley and Katie B. at their Beaver Creek home, 1935; 395(II)12 (Folder 12)
  - B.D. Phillips and friend at Ruby Gulch, undated; 395(II)13 (Folder 13)
  - Whitcomb home in Helena, Montana, 1912-1926; 395(II)14 (Folder 14)
  - Ore cart at mouth of mine in winter, Ruby Camp, undated; 395(II)15 (Folder 15)
  - Postcard of two men by ore cart, undated; 395(II)16 (Folder 16)
  - Charley (Gritty) Whitcomb, undated; 395(II)17 (Folder 17)
  - Charley Whitcomb's grave in Zortman Cemetary, undated; 395(II)18 (Folder 18)
  - Gold ore haulers in camp, undated; 395(II)19 (Folder 19)
  - Katie B. with the three daughters born in Townsend, undated; 395(II)20 (Folder 20)
  - House at Beaver Creek, 1971; 395(II)21 (Folder 21)
  - Katie B. with friends when she worked at Polaris, undated; 395(II)22 (Folder 22)
  - First Ruby Gulch Mill, 1904; 395(II)23 (Folder 23)
  - Hartmann's freight outfit with winter supplies for Zortman, ca.1908; 395(II)24 (Folder 24)
  - Joe Hartman transporting power plant boilers from Winifred, undated; 395(II)25 (Folder 25)
  - Power plant on Missouri River, 1914; 395(II)26 (Folder 26)
  - Catholic church at Zortman, 1971; 395(II)27 (Folder 27)
  - Tim, Mr. Smith, and L.A. (top row, l-r), Mrs. Hartman and Mrs. L.A., undated; 395(II)28 (Folder 28)
  - Hard Luck Smith, freighter, miner, and mill hand, undated; 395(II)29 (Folder 29)
  - Miners in front of Whitcomb store and post office near Ruby Gulch Mine, undated; 395(II)30 (Folder 30)
  - Zortman, Montana, 1907; 395(II)31 (Folder 31)
  - Gold bar on scale, undated; 395(II)32 (Folder 32)
  - Unknown man at smelter, undated; 395(II)33 (Folder 33)
  - "New mill", undated; 395(II)34 (Folder 34)
  - Second Ruby Gulch Mill, 1914; 395(II)35 (Folder 35)
  - Ruby Camp in winter, undated; 395(II)36 (Folder 36)
  - Gold ore en route to mill, undated; 395(II)37 (Folder 37)
  - Unknown man with herd of sheep, undated; 395(II)38 (Folder 38)
  - Tramway for cars carrying ore from the Alabama to the Ruby Mill, undated; 395(II)39 (Folder 39)
  - Dodson-Zortman stageline, undated; 395(II)40 (Folder 40)
  - View from the saddle above Ruby, undated; 395(II)41 (Folder 41)